<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The information of John Macnamara, Gent., touching the Popish plot in Ireland carried on by the conspiracies of the Earl of Tyrone, and others his confederates to deliver up that kingdom to the French king, and establish the Popish religion therein : being all matter of fact, delivered upon oath to His Majesty, and both Houses of Parliament, in Novemb. 1680.</title>
            <author>Macnamara, John, Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50998</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11871479</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11871479</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50998)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 501:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The information of John Macnamara, Gent., touching the Popish plot in Ireland carried on by the conspiracies of the Earl of Tyrone, and others his confederates to deliver up that kingdom to the French king, and establish the Popish religion therein : being all matter of fact, delivered upon oath to His Majesty, and both Houses of Parliament, in Novemb. 1680.</title>
                  <author>Macnamara, John, Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randolph Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Arrata [i.e. Errata] on p. 23.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tyrone, Richard Power, --  Earl of, 1630-1690.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1660-1690.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:50145:1"/>
            <p>Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament Aſſembled, That <hi>Hubart Bourk,</hi> and <hi>John Macnamara,</hi> have hereby leave given them, to Print and Publiſh their reſpective Informations or Narratives con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Popiſh Plot formerly by them given in at the Bar of this Houſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN BROWNE Cleric. Parlimentorum.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>By Vertue of the Order above mentioned, I do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point <hi>Randolph Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> to Print this my Information; and that no other perſon or perſons do Print the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN MACNAMARA.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 14. 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50145:1"/>
            <p>THE INFORMATION OF John Macnamara, Gent.</p>
            <p>Touching the POPISH PLOT IN IRELAND: Carried on by the Conſpiracies of the EARL of TYRONE, And others his Confederates, To deliver up that Kingdom to the <hi>French</hi> King, and Eſtabliſh the Popiſh Religion therein.</p>
            <p>Being all Matter of Fact, delivered upon Oath to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and both Houſes of Parliament, in <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1680.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Randolph Taylor,</hi> and are by him ſold at his Houſe near <hi>Stationers-Hall, Anno</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50145:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50145:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable ANTHONY Earl of Shaftsbury.</head>
            <opener>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</opener>
            <p>THere is no queſtion to be made, but that the Grand Enemies both of His Majeſties Perſon and Government, did believe that their Party had been ſufficiently prevalent in <hi>England</hi> to have tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon Perſons, whom they had render'd friendleſs and impoveriſh'd in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Where Authority had made a League with Greatneſs, and cover'd all it's faults; as if the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> could not be Guilty, becauſe he was a Perſon of ſo high a degree Kindred, Friends, Relations, Tenants and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants all aſſiſted Him; but the Detectours of his Conſpiracies, had not one Patron to take them into his Protection. <hi>England</hi> they ſoon found
<pb facs="tcp:50145:3"/>deeply apprehenſive of the Dangers that threatned one of the faireſt Kingdoms of the Britiſh Monarchy. And certainly it could not chooſe but be an Extraordinary Conſolation of their former diſcouragements to meet with, here, ſo many Eminent and worthy Patriots, Perſonages of chief renown and Dignitie, ſo readily giving ear to, and ſo judicially weighing and examining the diſcoveries of their Loyalty. For my own part, it was not only known to me, for It was known to all the Chriſtian World, how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous your Lordſhip had alwaies been for your indefatigable Zeal, and Vigilance over the ſafety of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt Sacred Perſon, and the welfare of the whole Extent of His Dominions.</p>
            <p>This I obſerved to be the reaſon why ſo many of His Majeſties Loyal En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Subjects made their Addreſſes to your Lordſhip. And if <hi>I</hi> among the <hi>Iriſh</hi> am not the firſt that have preſſed to implore the Countenance of your Lordſhips favour, it was only the want of a happy Opportunity to
<pb facs="tcp:50145:3"/>render my ſelf capable of ſo high an Honour. To which if now I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to aſpire, I hope it will prove an argument, that I firmly intend to maintain and juſtifie my Information, and therebyin ſome meaſure to make my ſelf worthy of that Noble Title of being.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt humble, moſt faithful, and moſt obedient Servant,</hi> John Macknamara.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50145:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50145:4"/>
            <head>THE INFORMATION OF John Macnamara, Gent.</head>
            <p>THis Informant ſaith, that in the Year 1676. one <hi>John Brenan,</hi> who was then lately come from <hi>Rome,</hi> was made Archbiſhop of <hi>Caſhell, Waterford</hi> and <hi>Liſmere,</hi> by one <hi>Plunkett,</hi> who by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Rome,</hi> pretended to be Primate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Brenan</hi> producing Bulls from the Pope to the ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Primate for that purpoſe, together with ſeveral other Bulls brought over at the ſame time by the ſaid <hi>Brenan,</hi> of which Dean <hi>Powre,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi>'s Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man informed this Informant, as hereafter ſhall appear. In the year aboveſaid this Informant obſerv'd the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous Gongregations of Prieſts and Fryers, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted to <hi>Knock-houſe,</hi> a Houſe of Entertainment, three Miles Weſtward of <hi>Waterford.</hi> This Informant took extraordinary notice of it, as being not a thing ſo uſual; inſomuch that being in company with ſeveral of the ſaid Prieſts, in the ſaid Houſe, and that at ſeveral times; but eſpecially with the aforeſaid Dean <hi>Powre,</hi> who was nex in dignity to the ſaid <hi>Brenan,</hi> this Informant began to enquire the reaſon of their Meetings ſo publick and ſo frequent in time of Perſecution. The ſaid <hi>Powre</hi> made anſwer, That he would ſatisfie this Informant as to that, next <hi>Patron</hi> day, at <hi>Resk;</hi> which happen'd to be upon the <hi>Lady-day</hi> following, and within a few days after the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50145:5"/>propoſal of the Queſtion. Accordingly this Informant met at the time and place appointed, and there receiv'd the following ſatisfaction. For the Congregations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gather'd together to confeſs and receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, after the Popiſh manner, one <hi>Edmund Poore,</hi> a Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, preached a Sermon, the ſubſtance of which was, to let the Congregation underſtand, that they had an indulgence from the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> granted them, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to eat fleſh on <hi>Wedneſdays.</hi> But in the concluſion told them, that there was a conſideration for which ſo great a Priviledg as that was granted; which the Prieſt of every Pariſh had orders to give in charge to his Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners at the time of confeſſion. Sermon being done, the Prieſts fell to the exerciſe of their main duty, which was to confeſs the Congregation, and this Informant being then one of that Religion, made his Confeſſion to the aforeſaid Dean <hi>Powre.</hi> Now at the time of his Confeſſion, the ſaid Dean gave this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant in charge as followeth, <hi>That he ſhould not divulge to any perſon whatſoever, on pain of mortal ſin and damnation; and as he would be thought worthy of the holy Sacrament which he was to receive, what he ſhould impart to this Informant;</hi> upon which this Informant promiſed him he would not With that he proceeded thus; <hi>That the aforeſaid Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and Liberty was granted upon this account, That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was in a capacity to help and aſsiſt the Holy Cauſe in the preſent Deſigns, and which had been in hand for a long time, might have the benefit of the aforeſaid Indulgencies, which was a pardon of ſins for many years.</hi> He further added, That the Clergy of <hi>Ireland</hi> were to have the benefits and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of the Tythes, accrewing out of each Pariſh, with the Gleabes and Monks Lands and Appurtenances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing unto them, which the Hereticks had wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully poſſeſs'd for a long time. That great preferments were intended for others; and that the <hi>French</hi> King, and the reſt of the Popiſh Confederates, together with the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50145:5"/>aſſiſtance of his Holineſs the Pope, did intend imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to invade the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and then proceeding, we do not doubt, ſaid he, but by the aſſiſtance of God to bring our deſign to paſs in a ſhort time, and to waſh the hands of Hereticks out of the Eſtates of our Anceſtors; for that the Duke of <hi>York</hi> gives full conſent, and is of our ſide, beſides that we have the aſſiſtance of the Earl of <hi>Angleſey,</hi> and ſeveral other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality in the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> for whom we are to have inſtructions to celebrate ſeveral hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Maſſes, which he the ſaid Dean had according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordered all the Pariſh Prieſts to do within his Titular Juriſdiction. After which time this Informant obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that there were ſeveral Maſſes ſaid; particularly for the welfare and proſperity of His Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and of the Earl of <hi>Angleſey,</hi> in ſeveral places of the ſaid County of <hi>Waterford;</hi> and in ſome of thoſe Congregations, this Informant has prayed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for the ſaid perſons, according to the directions of the ſaid Prieſts and Dean. The ſaid titular Dean more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over ſaid, That the Earl of <hi>Angleſey</hi> being aſſiſted by the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> did endeavour that the Parliament ſhould not ſit, to prevent the perſecution of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks.</p>
            <p>And this Informant further ſaith, That in the year 1677. the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> produced unto this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant a Letter ſent over by Captain <hi>Daniel Macnamara,</hi> ſetting forth, That what he expected from His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, (meaning the <hi>French</hi> King) was granted; and that Captain <hi>Garrett Fitz Girald,</hi> one of the <hi>French</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, was ſent over with the Articles of Agreement, which were concluded on by the <hi>French</hi> King, being all according to his Lordſhips deſire, which was, that his Lordſhip ſhould raiſe a thouſand Men in the County of <hi>Waterford;</hi> to which purpoſe the <hi>French</hi> King had ſent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50145:6"/>his Lordſhip a Commiſſion, under his Hand and Seal, to be a Collonel of Horſe; and blank Commiſſions, to be diſpos'd of as his Lordſhip thought convenient, together with the ſaid <hi>French</hi> King's Propoſitions, which were, That his Lordſhip would be ſatisfi'd to have the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and City of <hi>Waterford,</hi> to be his Lordſhips lot and ſhare for his good ſervice. And further ſaid, That if his Lordſhip did deſerve it, he would make him Lieutenant General of his Forces in that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, That in the ſame year, before that the ſaid Earl made this Informant privy unto this ſaid Letter, the ſaid Captain <hi>Garrett Fitz Girald,</hi> by whom the ſaid Meſſage was ſent, lodged at the ſaid Earl's houſe for one mouth, and that this Informant was ſeveral times in the ſaid Captain's company, both at <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terford</hi> and <hi>Caraghmore;</hi> and that the ſaid Captain did preſent the reſpects and ſervice of the ſaid Capt. <hi>Daniel Macnamara</hi> to this Informant, as from a perſon of his familiar acquaintance; and alſo told this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, that he the ſaid Capt. was ſent over by his King, meaning the <hi>French</hi> King, with a Meſſage to the Right Honourable <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Tyrone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This informant further ſaith, That the ſaid Capt. <hi>Fitz Girald</hi> deſir'd this Informant to let the Brother of this Informant go along with him the ſaid Capt. into <hi>France;</hi> and that he would get him an Enſigns place in the <hi>French</hi> King's Service. This Informant inform'd the ſaid Earl of that proffer made to this Informant's Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but the ſaid Earl made anſwer, that he ſhould not go, in regard he the ſaid Earl did not know how ſoon an opportunity might fall to prefer him to as good a place in his Native Country.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, That the ſaid Captain <hi>Garret Fitz Girald,</hi> when he ſaw his time, went away
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50145:6"/>from the ſaid Earls houſe in diſguize, after he had end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his buſineſs with the ſaid Earl, and took a Ship im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately for <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, that Capt. <hi>Daniel Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namara</hi> came out of <hi>France</hi> ſome time before, and this Informant meeting with him in the City of <hi>Waterford;</hi> after his the ſaid Captains Landing, went into one Mr. <hi>Goodricks</hi> houſe in <hi>Waterford,</hi> to give the ſaid Capt. his welcom into <hi>Ireland,</hi> as being one of this Informants Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Name, where he fell into a diſcourſe with the ſaid Capt. what his occaſions of coming over were at that time. The ſaid Capt. told this Informant, that he was ſent over by the <hi>French</hi> King, unto the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and from thence he would go to the County of <hi>Clare,</hi> and County of <hi>Linmick,</hi> and deliver his Meſſage there, and would immediately take ſhipping again at <hi>Dingleicuſe,</hi> and told this Informant withall, he ſhould ſee an alteration of the world very ſuddenly.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, That in the ſame year 1677. a friend of this Informants, whoſe Wife had then a Child of this Informan is at Nurſe, had a difference with another man, which occaſioned a quarrel between them, upon which they both falling to blows, this Informants friend beat the other perſon, who thereupon got a Warrant of the Peace againſt his Adverſary, from one <hi>Andrew Lynn</hi> Eſquire, which as ſoon as this Informant heard of, he went to another Juſtice of the Peace, one Mr. <hi>Bradley,</hi> being a friend of this Informants, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a Superfedeas of Mr. <hi>Lynn</hi>'s Warrant. The ſaid Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> preſently took this Informants word for the Appearance of his Acquaintance, and diſcharged him from the Warrant above mentioned; and having ſo done, took this Informant ſide, and then gave him an Oath of Secreſie, in reference to the Plot intended, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50145:7"/>deſign'd in <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and the reſt of the Confederates agianſt the King's Majeſty. At which time he imparted to this Informant, that the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> had receiv'd a Commiſſion from the <hi>French</hi> King, to be a Collonel of Horſe in the County of <hi>Waterford,</hi> and that he the ſaid <hi>William Bradley</hi> was to be his Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Collonel, and deſir'd this Informant to provide himſelf with Horſe and Arms, and to procure as many as he could of thoſe he durſt to truſt; and that this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant ſhould have a Command of a Captain under the ſaid Earl and him. Whereupon this Informant did provide himſelf, and ſpoke unto <hi>John Follio, James Finicon,</hi> and <hi>Denis Macnamara,</hi> to provide themſelves with ſuch neceſſaries as were requiſite for that purpoſe, informing them alſo, that Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> had imparted ſeveral matters of concernment unto this Informant; and thereupon this Informant furniſh'd them all three with Arms, but to the ſaid <hi>Denis Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namara</hi> gave both Horſe and Arms. And this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant alſo did accordingly impart the ſame matters to the ſaid <hi>John Folio, John Finicon,</hi> and <hi>Denis Macnamara,</hi> who being afterwards ſent for by his Grace the Lord Lieutenant and Council, did confeſs the ſame during this Informants Confinement; and that too before this Informant had liberty to ſpeak with them, or they with him, being then kept cloſe Priſoner from any one of the King's Evidence.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, That after the aforeſaid <hi>William Bradley</hi> did impart to this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant the aforeſaid Treaſon, this Informant met with the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> upon the Lands of <hi>Saveſton</hi> in the County of <hi>Waterford,</hi> with two of his Men, <hi>viz. Thomas Powre</hi> his Gentleman, and <hi>Garrett Mac Teege</hi> his Fowler; and another whoſe name is <hi>Luke Powre;</hi> this Informant having in company with him one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50145:7"/>
               <hi>William Powre,</hi> and <hi>Boetius Clancy,</hi> being then abroad a hunting with their Doggs. The ſaid Earl, knowing this Informant at a diſtance, called to him, upon which this Informant went to his Lordſhip. The ſaid Earl then taking this Informant from the company, asked him, whether Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> had imparted to him any matter of Secrecy? This Informant replyed, he had. Thereupon the ſaid Earl told this Informant, that he muſt be very private, and diſcover it to none but thoſe he was very well aſſured of. After which, the ſaid Earl drew a Liſt out of his pocket, and ſhewed this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant a Roll of the names of ſeveral perſons that were to be ſuperior Officers, both in the County of <hi>Waterford,</hi> County of <hi>Corks,</hi> County of <hi>Kerry,</hi> County of <hi>Limrick,</hi> and County of <hi>Clare,</hi> which this Informant took ſpecial no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, and knew ſeveral of the perſons; and amongſt the reſt, the Earl entred this Informants Name with his own Pen and Ink, in the Liſt; the ſaid Earl tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Informant he had his Commiſſion ſent him from the <hi>French</hi> King under hand and ſeal, to be a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel of a Regiment of Horſe in the County of <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi> And further added, that there was hardly a County in <hi>Ireland,</hi> wherein perſons were not appointed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion'd by the <hi>French</hi> King for that purpoſe. Among the reſt his Lordſhip named, in the County of <hi>Limrick,</hi> Collonel <hi>Peirce Lacy,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Brittas,</hi> Sir <hi>John Fitz Girald, David Fitz Girald,</hi> and ſeveral others. In the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Clare, John Macnamara,</hi> and ſeveral others. In the County of <hi>Kerry,</hi> Sir <hi>Turlo Mac Mahoon,</hi> and ſeveral others; and others in the County of <hi>Cork.</hi> And for the County of <hi>Waterford,</hi> the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> nam'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be Coll. of Horſe, Mr. <hi>Bradly</hi> to be his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Quarterm after <hi>Ely</hi> for his Major, and Mr. <hi>John But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſenior,</hi> to be one of his Captains, having at the ſame time in his hand a Liſt of the Names of ſeveral others. The ſaid Earl ſaying, they were to raiſe ſeveral hunderds
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50145:8"/>of Men in every County, and that the ſuperior Officers were to meet, on purpoſe that they might return an exact Account of their Forces to the <hi>French</hi> King. Which being done, and all things ready, the ſaid King would land man thouſands of his own Men upon the Coaſt of the River <hi>Shamion;</hi> and as ſoon as they were landed, the next buſineſs was to march to the City of <hi>Limrick,</hi> with a Party of 500 Men, divided into two parts; the one Party to enter the City by Candle-light, and that at ſeveral Gates; in which Attempt, ſuch as beſt knew the City were appointed to ſet upon the Guards, and keep them in play, while the other Party, which was to be hard by the City, came up to their relief, the Body of the Army being order'd to follow, with all the ſpeed imaginable. By which means, ſaid the Earl, we do not queſtion but to poſſeſs our ſelves of the City, and King's Caſtle, and to expel all the Engliſh very ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly. And indeed, ſaid the Earl, 'tis the providence of God to bring this downfal on that unjuſt King, the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and his Children, that wrong'd me in ſo high a nature, upon the account of <hi>Villiars.</hi> Therefore, ſaid the Earl, go home, loſe no time, but make your ſelves ready; for we know not how ſoon occaſion may require your aſſiſtance, and ſpeak to as many friends as you can, which accordingly this Informant did, and provided Horſe and Arms for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>After Diſcovery made hereof by <hi>Hubert Bourke</hi> as you may read in his Information, who partly knew of theſe proceedings, the ſaid <hi>Hubert,</hi> upon his Diſcovery, was bound by Recognizance to proſecute the ſaid Earl at the next Aſſizes at <hi>Waterford;</hi> but for want of this Informants and other teſtimonies; and for other Reaſons mention'd in his Examination, he was forc'd to abſent himſelf from the Aſſizes, unto which he was bound, as is before mention'd.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50145:8"/>In reference to which, this Informant ſaith, that in the month of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the year 1677, when the Earl of <hi>Tyrones</hi> Trial was to be at <hi>Waterford;</hi> when Mr. <hi>Hubert Bourk</hi> was alſo to proſecute the ſaid Earl, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bourk</hi> preferring a Petition to the Judges of Aſſize, and ſetting forth therein, that he wanted his Witneſſes, which were able to make out more than he could; naming Mr. <hi>Tho. Sampſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ed. Ivie,</hi> this Informant and ſome others, one <hi>Robert Powre</hi> was ſent from the ſaid Earl to this Informant with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs from the ſaid Earl, that this Informant ſhould not appear in Court, for fear of being called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion upon the ſame account. This Informant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore abſented himſelf for the ſpace of that day, until ſuch time as there was intelligence brought him by Mr. <hi>Boetius Clancy,</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Bourk</hi> was run away. Upon which, this Informant repaired to <hi>Waterford,</hi> and kept himſelf private for ſome time, but ſent word to the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> that he this Informant was in the ſaid City. Upon which, the ſaid Earl ſent one <hi>Edmund Powre</hi> to this Informant deſiring him to come to his Lodging, which this Informant ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly did, where he found the ſaid Earl and the Judges of Aſſize at Dinner at that time. Thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this Informant coming to the Chamber-door, deſited the man of the Houſe, who was one Mr. <hi>Fiſh,</hi> to inform his Lordſhip that this Informant attended without.</p>
            <p>Upon delivery of the ſaid Meſſage to the ſaid Earl, one Captain <hi>Tho. Powre,</hi> one of the ſaid Earls Relations, was ſent to this Informant, to let him know, that it was contrived by the ſaid Earl, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by the ſaid Judges, that this Informant ſhould not come near the ſaid Earl for that time, for fear notice ſhould be taken of it by ſome perſons tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50145:9"/>were in Court, and that it was directed by the ſaid Judges, that this Informant ſhould go to <hi>Caragh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> to the ſaid Earls houſe, where the ſaid Earl would have a private conference with him upon the whole Buſineſs, which accordingly this Informant did, and after his coming to the ſaid <hi>Caraghmore,</hi> this Informant ſent word by Major <hi>John Butler,</hi> to the ſaid Earl, that he this Informant was there ready to attend his Lordſhip. Upon which, the ſaid Earl ordered a back door, leading to his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Garden to be opened, by which this Informant was ordered to go in to the ſaid Garden, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſaid Major. <hi>John Butler.</hi> After a little time, the ſaid Earl entred at another door, and after ſome Ceremonies, asked this Informant, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he the ſaid Information gave any Tolleration to the ſaid <hi>Bourke,</hi> to produce him this Informant as a witneſs? To which this Informant made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, no. Why, ſaid the ſaid Earl, Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> ſwore to me at <hi>Mathew Hores</hi> Houſe, that you did, or elſe that Mr. <hi>Bourke</hi> could never have known ſo much as he does. To which this Informant ſwore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that he never did; but that he had courted Mr. <hi>Ivie,</hi> being this Informants Tenant, to trappan Mr. <hi>Sampſon</hi> which was the ſaid Earls late Steward, and that the ſaid <hi>Ivie</hi> had engaged to contrive the matter ſo, as to bring the ſaid <hi>Sampſon</hi> to <hi>Keale</hi> in <hi>Craghs</hi> houſe at <hi>Kilmacthomas,</hi> and there to make him drunk, and that he the ſaid <hi>Ivie</hi> would make him confeſs that he knew nothing againſt the ſaid Earl, in reference to any Plot, that when the ſaid Confeſſion was to be made, Mr. <hi>Pierce Powre,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Powre</hi> and this Informant, were to be in a private Room next adjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to hear and make information of the ſaid <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> Confeſſion. Whereupon the ſaid Earl was very well ſatisfied, and commending the ſaid contrivance, ſaid that <hi>Bourk</hi> had not the wit to proſecute him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50145:9"/>the aſſiſtance of the ſaid <hi>Sampſon.</hi> However to prevent any further danger, ſaid the Earl. I would have you write unto the ſaid <hi>Bourk,</hi> and bring him to ſome compoſition. This Informant made anſwer, that he knew not where the ſaid <hi>Bourk</hi> was. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ſaid Earl told this Informant, that he was at <hi>Gurtens</hi> in the County of <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> and that he heard that the ſaid <hi>Bourk</hi> had a deſign for <hi>England,</hi> to apply himſelf to the King and Council therefore to prevent that miſchief, ſaid he go home, and write a Letter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to him; and let the Contents of the Letter be, that you have urgent occaſions with him, and that you muſt of neceſſity have ſome private conference with him. According to the ſaid Earls inſtructions, this Informant went home, and writ a Letter to the ſaid <hi>Bourk,</hi> deſiring him to come to this Informants houſe: but the ſaid <hi>Bourk</hi> refuſed ſo to do. Nevertheleſs, this Informant underſtanding afterwards by a Meſſenger ſent by the ſaid <hi>Bourk,</hi> where he was, being then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from the aforeſaid <hi>Gurtens,</hi> whither the Earl had ſaid he was retir'd, This Informant went to <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terford,</hi> and there meeting with the ſaid <hi>Bourke,</hi> court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him ſo long to go with him to this Informants houſe, that after many perſwaſions, the ſaid <hi>Bourk</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to go along with this Informant. Of which, two days after, this Informant went and gave notice to the Earl. Whereupon, the ſaid Earl gave this Informant theſe following Inſtructions. That this Informant ſhould endeavour to get the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> to confeſs that one Squier <hi>Villiers,</hi> Capt. <hi>Nichols,</hi> Mr. May, Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> and <hi>Peter Anthony</hi> were the perſons that had hited him the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> to accuſe the ſaid Earl; and that if he would acknowledg the ſame, and give it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his hand, the ſaid Earl promiſed he would give him the ſaid <hi>Bourke</hi> a Farm well ſtockt, together with a conſiderable ſum of mony, and would ſave him harmleſs from any danger that could enſue.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50145:10"/>This Informant in anſwer to the ſaid Earl, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> was concerned in the Plot, asked his Lordſhip the Reaſon, why he ſhould go about to bring the ſaid <hi>Bradleys</hi> Name in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? The ſaid Earl made Anſwer, that Mr. <hi>Lyn,</hi> his very good friend, and Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> had contrived it ſo, that if <hi>Bourk</hi> did acknowledg the ſame, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> ſhould confirm what the ſaid <hi>Bourk</hi> ſhould ſay, and that he the ſaid Earl ſhould bring his Action of <hi>Sandalum Magnatum,</hi> to the vallue of 40000 pound againſt the reſt. After which the ſaid Earl appointed Major <hi>John Butler</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Ronan,</hi> to meet Mr. <hi>Bourk</hi> and this Informant at <hi>Cariginure</hi> Mill, being alſo an Alehouſe. And that this Infarmant ſhould appear as the ſaid <hi>Bourks</hi> friend, and the other two for the ſaid Earl, which accordingly we did.</p>
            <p>There we had a long conference about the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but the ſaid <hi>Bourk</hi> being very obſtinate, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to concur with our deſire, though we proffered him the ſaid Farm and Stock and a thouſand pound to boot,</p>
            <p>We broke off, and the ſaid Major <hi>Butler</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bourk</hi> went along with this Informant to his Houſe that night. The next morning the ſaid Major <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> departed with an Account to the ſaid Earl, that we could not bring the ſaid <hi>Bourk</hi> to any compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Upon which the ſaid Earl immediately petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the Lord Lieutenant, that whereas the ſaid <hi>Bourk,</hi> according to his Recognizance, had not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to proſecute him, that there might be ſome courſe taken therein. Upon which, there was an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der granted for apprehending the ſaid <hi>Bourk,</hi> who thereupon was taken at this Informants Houſe, and carried to <hi>Dublin</hi> by the Purſivants, and examined the reaſon of his abſenting himſelf from the Aſſizes,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50145:10"/>where he was bound to proſecute the Earl of <hi>Tirone.</hi> He anſwered, that he wanted the reſt of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and being examined who they were? he ſaid, there wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Mr. <hi>Sampſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ivy</hi> and this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant with ſeveral other Witneſſes, upon which the ſaid <hi>Sampſon</hi> and <hi>Ivy</hi> were ſent for, and appeared; and upon their appearance gave in an Information againſt Quartermaſter <hi>Ely, John Ronan,</hi> Major <hi>John Butler, Dawrence Sulivin,</hi> this Informant and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other perſons. Upon which Information, a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter miſſive was ſent for the aforeſaid perſons toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with this Informant, and directed to Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter <hi>Ely,</hi> notwithſtanding he was accuſed.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Quartermaſter having received the Letter, immediately repaired to <hi>Caraghmore</hi> to the ſaid Earls Houſe, and ſhewed him his Order, upon which the ſaid Earl ſent <hi>Tho. Powre</hi> his Gentleman for this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant: But this Informant being not at home at that time, the ſaid <hi>Thomas Powre</hi> followed this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant to <hi>Waterford,</hi> where he found this Informant in Company with the High-Sheriff of the ſaid County and one Squire <hi>Welſh,</hi> a Relation and correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the ſaid Earls, and told this Informant his Meſſage, and that he muſt immediately repair to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raghmore,</hi> for that there were Orders from <hi>Dublin</hi> for this Informant and the aforementioned perſons to appear there, and anſwer a Charge laid againſt them by the aforeſaid <hi>Sampſon, Bourk</hi> and <hi>Ivy.</hi> Upon which the ſaid Squire <hi>Welſh,</hi> Son to Sir <hi>Robert Welſh</hi> now or late living in this City of <hi>London,</hi> begg'd of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant to appear for the ſaid Earl, with promiſes of great rewards for ſo doing, which this Informant promiſed he would do; the ſaid <hi>Wealſh</hi> afterwards being one of the Grand Jury for the Trial of the ſaid Earl. But this Informant having ſent his Horſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50145:11"/>home that night by his Servant, told the ſaid Earls man that he had never a Horſe to go along with him. Upon which the ſaid Earle's man procured a Horſe for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Informant. In our journey to <hi>Caraghmore</hi> we met with one <hi>Jaſper Grant,</hi> that had been a Captain of one of his Majeſties Men of War, who told this Informant that the ſaid Earl had employed him the ſaid <hi>Grant</hi> to ſpeak with this Informant, and to go ſeek him where ever he could find him, and further ſaid, that if this Informant did appear for the ſaid Earl in <hi>Dublin,</hi> he would reward him at a high rate. This Captain was alſo afterwards admitted of the Jury for the Trial of the ſaid Earl.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, that after he arrived at <hi>Caraghmore</hi> at the ſaid Earls houſe, the ſaid Earl to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſaid Quartermaſter <hi>Ely,</hi> took him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Garden; and there did engage this Informant not to diſcover any kind of thing that he knew, and ſwear to the contrary of having any knowledg of any Treaſon, &amp; that Father <hi>Robert Powre,</hi> the Titular Dean, would give an Abſolution to the ſaid Informant for ſo doing, for that it was not a ſin to ſwear any thing to ſave a mans Life; and further told this Informant that Judg <hi>Keating</hi> and Sir <hi>John Davis</hi> were the ſaid Earls great Eriends, and would ſtick cloſe to this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant, and gave the ſaid Informant Letters to be delivered to the ſaid Judg, which were to Invalidate the Teſtimony of the aforeſaid <hi>Bourk,</hi> and which this Informant delivered accordingly, and found that what the ſaid Earl ſaid was true; for during the time that this Informant denied the Treaſon, and kept it undiſcovered, the ſaid Judg did Act for him as much as he could; ſo that at night after the Council was up, the aforeſaid Quartermaſter, <hi>Ronan, Sulivan</hi> and this Informant went to Sir. <hi>John Davis,</hi> being Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50145:11"/>of State, and one of the Earls great friends, all the while that this Informant was of the ſaid Earls Partie; who gave us the aforeſaid Witneſſes a full Account of what was done againſt us every day in Council.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, that the ſaid Earl, at this Informants coming to <hi>Dublin,</hi> exchanged one of his Gueldings with Mr. <hi>Michael Roe,</hi> becauſe this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant ſhould ride the ſaid <hi>Roes</hi> Horſe, for fear that there would be notice taken of this Informants riding the ſaid Earls Horſe; and gave this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant mony to bear his expences to <hi>Dublin,</hi> with promiſes of greater rewards for appearing for him; and withal, admoniſhed this Informant in what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger he was if he ſhould diſcover the ſaid Treaſon, as well as the ſaid Earl, which very much terrified this Informant and kept him from making any Diſcovery for a long time.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, that the ſaid Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter <hi>Ely,</hi> after the Commitment of this ſaid Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant into the Purſivants hands by Order of the Lord Lieutenant and Council, was with him every day, charging this Informant not to diſcover, for his Life, the ſaid Treaſon, for that if he did, he would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be hang'd; and gave this Informant money to bear his charges till the ſaid Earl could furniſh him this Informant with more.</p>
            <p>And this Informant further ſaith, that one <hi>John Powre</hi> Eſquire, a Relation of the Earls, together with Mr. <hi>Cowdal</hi> and Mr. <hi>Roe,</hi> proferred 700 <hi>l.</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for this Informant, during his Confinement, and brought this Informant a Petition to prefer to the Lord Lieutenant and Council, wherein they had ordered this Informant to move that the ſaid ſecurity might be taken, with Reflections upon the Kings
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50145:12"/>Witneſſes in a high nature; which this Informant kept, but never preferred. And further ſaith, that being alone in the Condition that he was, this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant made his Addreſſes by Prayer to Heaven, to direct him the ſaid Informant, being then at a ſtand, whether it were better for him to Diſcover the Treaſon or to Conceal it, for the guilt lay ſo heavy upon this Informant's Conſcience, that he was in as much fear of himſelf, as of thoſe that were moſt concerned But at laſt, and he believes it to be the Effect of his Prayers, God put it into his mind, that in was the trueſt way to diſcover what he knew. Upon which this Informant gave in this his Information concerning the Plot, and his knowledge of ſuch Perſons as were to be Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the Army intended to be raiſed by the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and <hi>William Bradley</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> for the uſe of the French King.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, that at what time he went to the ſaid Earl to give him an Account of what this Informant and the reſt had done with <hi>Bourk,</hi> when they were ordered to tamper and make a Compoſition with him, the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> ſhewed this Informant a Letter from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Law the Earl of <hi>Angleſey,</hi> Signed <hi>Angleſey,</hi> and which the ſaid Earl averd to this Informant, to be his own Letter and Subſcription, wherein this Informant read, that the ſaid Earl of <hi>Angleſey,</hi> had made ſo many Friends in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> for him the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> that there was no need to fear what was laid to his Charge, and that he had ſpoken with the Duke of <hi>York</hi> about In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceding for him, which the Duke had promiſed he would do.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:50145:12"/>This Informant further ſaith, that the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> did imploy ſeveral perſons whoſe names were <hi>James Powre, Richard Powre, William Powre</hi> and <hi>Owen Whelam,</hi> formerly a <hi>Tory,</hi> and one of the ſaid Earls followers, with ſeveral others, to ſteal Horſes from ſeveral parts of the Kingdom for the ſervice of the Army deſigned and promiſed by him to be raiſed, to joyn with the French Kings For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which were expected to be Landed in <hi>Ireland.</hi> In purſuance of which directions of his Lordſhip, the ſaid perſons did accordingly ſteal ſeveral Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of good value out of ſeveral parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and brought them all into the County of <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> to the number of thirty or thereabouts, which by order of the ſaid Earl were diſtributed among ſuch perſons as were by him engaged in, and privy to his deſign. Particularly, ſome to <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Finch,</hi> the ſaid Earls menial Servant and a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, ſome to one Mr. <hi>John Welſh,</hi> Nephew to the ſaid Earl; ſome to this Informant, ſome to Mr. <hi>William Dobbin,</hi> and ſome to Mr. <hi>William-Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys</hi> Servant <hi>John Labor,</hi> which by the Order of his Maſter he received at <hi>Raghneskdoig,</hi> and ſome to <hi>John Powre</hi> of <hi>Clonmel.</hi> But ſome of the own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the ſaid Horſes making purſuit after their ſtollen goods, and apprehending by Virtue of a Warrant ſome of the Perſons who had ſtollen their ſaid Horſes, they were by Sir <hi>Thomas Osborn</hi> Committed to the Cuſtody of one <hi>Patrick Kar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> then High Conſtable, and one of Mr. <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Bradleys</hi> Foſterers, to be by him Conveyed to the Goal of <hi>Waterford,</hi> from whence they were to be removed to <hi>Maroborough</hi> Goal in <hi>Queens County.</hi> Whereupon, the ſaid Mr. <hi>William Bradley</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the ſaid Perſons were Apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50145:13"/>and as he knew well upon what account, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doubtful leaſt they might betray the Buſineſs, immediately wrote to the ſaid High Conſtable, his Foſterer, to ſet thoſe Perſons at liberty. Upon which, the ſaid High Conſtable, in the way to <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terford,</hi> notwithſtanding he had a ſufficient Guard of Six petty Conſtables and others Aſſiſtants, gave liberty to the Felons in Cuſtody to make their eſcape upon a couple of the ſtollen Horſes that were led along with them, bridled and ſaddled for that purpoſe. For doing of which, he had the engagement of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bradley,</hi> and the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> to ſave him harmleſs. Wherein they were as good as their words; for the ſaid High Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable being queſtioned at the next Aſſizes at <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terford,</hi> the ſaid Earl and Mr. <hi>Bradley,</hi> by their great intereſt in the High <hi>Sheriff,</hi> who was then that very <hi>William Dobbins</hi> already mentioned, who had ſome of the ſaid Horſes in his Cuſtody, and being a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate provided the High Conſtable ſuch a Jury that he was ſoon acquitted: beſides that the Judge of the Aſſize, the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Keating</hi> was no leſs the Earl of <hi>Tyrones</hi> friend, then the High Sheriff.</p>
            <p>And this Informant further ſaith, that after this Informants appearing againſt the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> in the City of <hi>Dublin, John Folio</hi> and Mr. <hi>Denis Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namara,</hi> being in the company of this Informant, thoſe Felons (of which mention hath been alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made) did acknowledge the particulars aforeſaid. Whereupon this Informant together with one Mr. <hi>Edward Ivie,</hi> went to the Lord Chancellor of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for Advice how to procure a Warrant for the apprehending the ſaid Felons. But in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim of time, the Wife of <hi>Richard Powre,</hi> one of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50145:13"/>the ſaid Felons, went and Inform'd the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned <hi>William Dobbins,</hi> High Sherif of the County of <hi>Waterford,</hi> that the ſaid Felons did intend to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear againſt the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone.</hi> Upon which the ſaid <hi>Dobbins,</hi> with the aſſiſtance of one Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Morrice,</hi> a friend of the ſaid Earls, procured a Warrant to ſeize upon the ſaid Felons, before this Informant ſhould do it himſelf. Which was done, and they Committed to <hi>Newgate</hi> in <hi>Dublin;</hi> which this Informant no ſooner underſtood, but he, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Mr. <hi>Hubert Bourk,</hi> went to the ſaid Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in <hi>Newgate,</hi> who acknowledged before this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant and <hi>Hubert Bourk,</hi> that they were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to prevent the appearance againſt the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bradley,</hi> and that they had the ſame matters to inform, if they could be admitted their Liberty. At the ſame time, this Informant and Mr. <hi>Bourk,</hi> being with the ſaid Felons at the ſame Conference, the aforeſaid Mr. <hi>Dobbins</hi> and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Morrice</hi> came into the next Room, and ſent for the ſaid Felons out of this Informants Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and there concluded an Agreement with the ſaid Felons, that they ſhould not appear againſt the Earl or Mr. <hi>Bradley,</hi> upon Conſideration, that the ſaid <hi>Dobbins</hi> and <hi>Morrice</hi> ſhould clear them out of Goal, and obtain their acquitment from the Crime laid to their Charge. Which the ſaid Felons did acknowledge to this Informant and Mr. <hi>Bourk</hi> the next Morning. The truth whereof appeared, for that the ſaid Perſons were immediately Bailed by the ſaid <hi>Dobbins</hi> and <hi>Morrice,</hi> and ſo diſcharg'd out of Goal.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, that although he cannot make the Information himſelf, yet he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves he may be able to bring ſufficient Teſtimony
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50145:14"/>of the quantity of Arms and Ammunition that was received by Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> upon the account of the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> for the ſervice of the French King, and where they were by him Concealed, till occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhould require.</p>
            <p>And this informant further ſaith, that being in the City of <hi>London</hi> in <hi>April</hi> laſt paſt, to complain of his own grievances, and the miſcarriages of the Iriſh Jury in the acquittal of the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> his Majeſty and the Council were pleaſed to order him back again, to make out before the Lieutenant and Council in <hi>Dublin</hi> what he had here made known, which accordingly he did, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Major part of the ſaid. Jury were the Relations and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents of the ſaid Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> and Mr. <hi>William Bradley,</hi> pickt and cul'd not only out of the proper County, but out of ſeveral other remote parts and places of the Kingdome. During which time, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a quarter of a year, he was not only expoſed to the Malice of his Enemies, but alſo to very great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, without any Allowance or Conſideration from the Lord Lieutenant. Whereas on the other ſide a poor and needy Scotchman coming in and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending a Sham-Plot of the Presbyterians, and deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Popiſh Plot, was immediately kindly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd and cheriſhed, and well Rewarded for his pains Which ſaid Scotchman came alſo at the ſame time to this Informant, and endeavoured to perſwade this Informant to joyn with him, and deſiſt from Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the Papiſts, ſaying, it would be far more advantagious to this Informant ſo to do than to Proſecute the Popiſh Plot, in regard it was not minded, as being an Affair wherein the Duke of <hi>York</hi> was concerned. However in a ſhort time after the ſaid Scotchman gave them the ſlip and run away.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50145:14"/>This Informant further ſaith, that in the ſame year, 1677. at the time when <hi>William Bradley</hi> Eſquire, imparted to this Informant the Deſign which was carried on by the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and the ſaid Mr. <hi>William Bradley,</hi> together with the reſt of the Confederates, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bradley</hi> gave this Informant to underſtand, that the French King would ſend Ammunition and Arms to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Army deſign'd for the Service of the ſaid French King in <hi>Ireland:</hi> and that there were ſeveral perſons in <hi>Ireland,</hi> appointed for receiving the ſame; and that among the reſt, he the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bradley,</hi> was appointed for one; and that he did expect the ſaid Arms very ſpeedily, together with the Ammunition promiſed. He alſo ſaid, that the Roman-Catholick Clergy, both in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> made it part of their buſineſs to write Letters both to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and had their Agents abroad in thoſe parts to ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit and procure the raiſing of ſeveral thouſands of pounds as well in <hi>Italy</hi> as in <hi>France,</hi> to furniſh and ſupply the wants of ſuch as were employ'd by the Pope, the French King and the reſt of the Confederates. And that the ſaid Arms ſhould be landed in the Creek of <hi>Ballirone,</hi> which lay within half a mile of his Houſe, between the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Waterford</hi> and the Town of <hi>Dungarvan,</hi> which is alſo a Seaport-Town.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, that at the time of his Conference with the Titular Dean of <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terford, Robert Powre</hi> by Name, he told this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant, that one Dr. <hi>White</hi> was employed as an Agent betwixt the perſons concerned in <hi>Ireland</hi> and the Pope, to give the ſaid Pope an accompt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50145:15"/>how Affairs were carried on, and in what Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Kingdom ſtood. The ſaid Titular Dean al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo further ſaid, that there was hardly a Province in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but there was one or other employ'd for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, that about two years ſince, the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> did acknowledg to this Deponent, that one <hi>James Lavalline,</hi> who was to murther the King, was ſent over into <hi>Ireland</hi> to be there ſecured from being apprehended; and that the ſaid Earl did receive Letters to that purpoſe from his Highneſs the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>York;</hi> upon which, he forthwith ſent the ſaid <hi>Lavalline</hi> to his Kinſman Mr. <hi>John Powre</hi> to be there kept private.</p>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, that the perſons concerned in this Conſpiracy for the County of <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terford,</hi> were the Earl of <hi>Tyrone, William Bradley,</hi> Eſquire, Quartermaſter <hi>Ely,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Butler, Paul Strange, Richard Powre, Peirce Welſh, John Powre, VVilliam Powre, Peirce Powre, Edmund Powre, VVilliam Fits. Gerrald, Michael Row, Richard Manſwell, John Folio, James Fumigan, Denis Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namarra, John Lahor,</hi> and this Informant, with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others.</p>
            <p>In the County of <hi>Limerick</hi> the Lord <hi>Brittas Bourk,</hi> Collonel <hi>Peirce Lacy, John Harly,</hi> Sir <hi>John Fits-Gerrald, David Fits Gerrald,</hi> and ſeveral others.</p>
            <p>In the County of <hi>Cork, VVilliam Fits-Gerrald, VVilliam Barry, James Barry, Theoby Roch, David Coudon, Denis Mac Cartie, Teige Mac-Cartie,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50145:15"/>In the County of <hi>Kerry,</hi> Sir <hi>Tirlagh Mac-Mahon, Daniel Mac-Conor, Teige Mac-Conor, John Sulivan, Derby Sulivan, Daniel Sulivan,</hi> and <hi>Garret Skack,</hi> with ſeveral others.</p>
            <p>In the County of <hi>Clare, John Macnamara, Tirlagh Obrian,</hi> with ſeveral others.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>ARRATA, <hi>P.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>read for</hi> 1677. <hi>read</hi> 1679. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 26. <hi>for Fiſh, read Frith.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
